Hello, for this task we are writing
a function which can compute the sum
of any finite list of numbers. So for example, if
you have an input list containing 2, 5, and 3,
you should get an output of 10. And to do this, we
are supposed to use a divide and conquer strategy,
which is already implemented for us
up here in this higher order function,
aptly named 'divideAndConquer' and all we need to
do really is call this 'divideAndConquer' function
with the correct functions as arguments to
solve our tasks. And if we look down here
in our 'sum' definition we can see there's
a call to 'divideAndConquer' already here
and for 'undefined', which corresponds to
the four functions 'divideAndConquer' should
receive. So our first 'undefined' corresponds
to 'simpleEnough', which should be the predicate
to test whether that input is simple enough,
and it should be of type integer list to Bool.
Our second 'undefined' corresponds to
'simpleCases', which needs to be the function
to compute the output directly for simple cases,
and it should be of type integer list to integer.
Now at this point you may notice that
these types given down here in the comments
don't actually match the type signatures
for these functions given up here in the
type signature of 'divideAndConquer', but this is
fine because these single letters are generics,
which means they can accept any
type; as long as we end up replacing
the same letter with the same type throughout
this type signature this will get accepted,
so in this case, all of the a's will end up being
replaced with integer lists and all the b's will
end up being replaced with just integers, and
technically that means our 'divideAndConquer'
implementation up here could be used for other
things, so we shouldn't touch any of this,
but we're going to end up having integer lists and
integers inserted here in the background for us.
Moving on with the functions, our third
'undefined' corresponds to the 'split'
function, which should be the function to
split a non-simple input into two smaller ones,
and it should be of type integer list to
a tuple containing two integer lists. And
finally for our 'combined' function that should
be the function to combine the outputs of two
subcomputations, and it should be of type integer
and integer to integer. And since we're summing
up here this combined function will probably
just end up being a simple addition operator,
so first of all let's look into 'divideAndConquer'
and see what these functions internally do.
We can see the sole call is just defined
as 'recursively' and then 'recursively'
is defined as 'recursively' on input, with an
if check with simple enough as the predicates,
and if simple enough with the input is true,
then simple cases are called on the input,
and if it's not true then we go into this else
block. The input is split by our split function
into left and right, and since we're working with
divide and conquer strategy here we usually want
to split our inputs into equal halves, so this
left and right should be roughly of equal size.
And then these left and right are used in
recursive calls to 'recursively' again,
and the results of which end up being in a
recursive stack here with the combined function,
which is just going to be our addition in the
end. So now that we know what 'divideAndConquer'
does internally we need to start looking
at what to replace our 'undefined's with,
so let's just start with the simplest one.
Our 'combined' function is just going to be
a simple addition operator because this will end
up giving it single items, so this can just be an
addition operator. And now where should we start
defining this? First of all, we could do something
like this, we could call this 'addition' and then
define 'addition' somewhere else as being the
addition operator or since we are not actually
using this function anywhere outside of sum,
and also we are only passing these as arguments
to 'divideAndConquer', these technically don't
need to be defined outside of this, and they don't
even need to have a name, so in this case we can
use lambda functions, or anonymous functions if
you will, so we could write something like this:
a + b to define our addition operator, and
that corresponds to the correct type signature,
this accepts two inputs, and then it
gets you a single integer in the end.
Now this reasoning of course also applies to the
three other 'undefined's; we don't need
to define them outside of this, and they
don't need to be named, so let's just
use lambda functions for all of these.
So let's just start with a basic frame; let's
call this 'list'; the other ones are receiving
integer lists according to our type signatures
down here, so let's just define them as such.
So we start with this as a basic framework.
And our first one corresponds to 'simpleEnough'
and this needs to be some kind of predicate;
so this needs to return a Boolean. To know when
this should be true, we need to first look at
what can 'simpleCases' even do with the input.
'simpleCases' according to type signature
gets an integer list and returns an integer.
So this is probably going to just unpack our list,
since simple cases shouldn't call anything else
internally; we should just pass these and not
do anything fancy inside of these functions
other than what our comments tell us, so compute
the output directly for simple cases. So what's
the output for a simple case in this case?
The simplest case we can have with a list is just
the empty list, so we could do a length check,
less than one, for example; this would cover
our empty list, and then we can define our
simple cases as if this is true, then the list is less
than one in length, so this is a list of length 0,
so we can just return 0 since we're summing up
and an empty list shouldn't affect our summation.
But this is not quite right yet, because obviously
we have another simple case where you can
take the result directly, which would be the list
with an element of one. So we can extend this to
length of our list, so I missed that length of
the list is less than or equal to one. So that's
either the empty list or a list with only one element,
and then in our simple cases we could do something
like: if the length of the list equals 0, then
we return a 0; else we return half of the list,
to extract the only item in the list, and at
this point we can actually also shorten this
to 'null list', which is just an internally defined
function from the prelude that checks if a list
has no elements in it, then we return true, so
in this case 'null list' would return true if the
list is empty; then return a 0; otherwise, we take
the first element of the list. So that's basically
our 'simpleEnough' and 'simpleCases' taken
care of; that's the simplest cases we can get,
obviously, a list with two elements wouldn't
work in 'simpleCases' because then we would
need to start doing something with it; we would
need to use our 'combine' function inside of
'simpleCases', but that's not the point of this;
we leave the combining to our strategy up here;
So this is all we can do with 'simpleEnough' and
'simpleCases', and now we just need to define our
'split' function. Like I mentioned earlier, in
a divide-and-conquer approach, you usually want
to split into equal halves to reduce the amount
of recursion steps you need to do in the end.
So since we have an input list here,
we can use 'splitAt' to just split
our list, and for the point where we want to
split, we can use the length of the list...
divided by half, so this will end up giving
us roughly the middle point for our list.
Obviously, it's not going to be the
exact middle point if it's an uneven
length list, but this is close enough.
Well, it's as close as we can get to evenly
splitting an uneven list. So now we replaced
all four of our 'unfined', and just to make sure
let's just go through the type signatures again;
The first one accepts the list of integers and
returns a Boolean, so this is the operator call
that will later get us our output, and this
is gonna be something that is Boolean, so
this matches our type signature at least.
The second one also receives something of
a list type and returns an integer; here in this
case, it either returns a 0 or it returns the head of
the list, so this would also end up fitting the type
signature. This also receives a list of integers
and 'splitAt' returns a tuple of the same type
as it's splitting, so our list is of type integer
list, so 'splitAt' will give us the correct type
that we need for our signature down here. And well,
the addition is simple enough; we don't need to
talk about that, so if we just save this now...
uh, yeah, see I didn't want to show you that, but
let's just reload our task in ghci and just try it
out; let's just try the main test, which is just
it's just this one test; it's a little too simple,
so let's try it with something else. Um, let's
try the example from the comments up here,
so [2,5,3] should end up with 10. All right,
that works; now if we wanted to, we could
also extend this a little bit. If you don't, if
you want to check a couple of times, you can easily
write your own tests down here if you want; so
let's just add this down here, then we save it,
reload and run the main function, we can see
we now have two tests, and both of these pass,
so if we had to make any more changes up here and
wanted to test again, we wouldn't have to do that
manually, but that's just a little aside. Now you
can already see my editor's telling me something
that I wanted to avoid showing you immediately;
this says 'void lambda', so this is telling us
this could be actually reduced down to just this
now and the error goes away. Now why is this? Our
lambda, in the way we had it, expects two arguments
to then use with the addition operator, but the
addition operator is already an operator that
expects two arguments, so we're basically wrapping
something that needs two arguments into something
that needs two arguments, so we can remove the
middleman, so to say, and just use this addition
directly; and if we just try this out again to see
if it works... yep, it still works so this little
hint that we got here from HLint is correct;
So this is also a reason why you should copy
these tasks out into your own editors and probably
keep HLint installed and running over your tasks,
at least on save or something, so you can avoid
simple things like this, or it can give you hints
which would end up being comments in your task
once you receive them back, but yeah,
this solves our task and we're done.